[music]
>> So, Bernard, I don't know. It's 2027.
What what do chips look like? What's
what's different? I mean, 2027 is
close-ish, uh at least on chip
timelines. Uh maybe not on AI timelines,
but for sure on chip timelines.
>> Those are Those are on a week-by-week
basis. Yeah, I know, right?
Um so, I mean, that is really sort of
answering the question of we're like,
what are the chips that have been in
development in the last year or two? Um
uh
I think the
like what are the big physics trends,
right? Like uh
flops are cheap. Um we can still pack
more and more of them into a chip uh
into the same amount of logic. Um uh
power density is going up as well. Like
we can just deliver more power to the
chips um and take the heat out. Um
and then uh just figure out how to use
that SRAM. Those are I think the big
three opportunities that we um
like is just like taking existing
technology and bringing it to to like
actual product market fits now. So, I
think that's in the short term is what
we should expect to see chips that um
are like many chips that are as low
latency as Groq and Cerebras. Um that's
through weights and SRAM.
Um
There's a whole thing there of like
weights and SRAM but probably KVs in
HBM.
Um
And then more and more flops just
because the sort of the What is the
exchange rate between like uh a marginal
flop versus a marginal um
uh
byte per second of HBM bandwidth? Uh the
sort of the cost of more flops is is is
a lot cheaper. And so, uh you can figure
out how to use that better. What what
what does the ratio look like right now?
Yeah, so
like I guess on the HBM side um
a a marginal uh byte per second of HBM
bandwidth really just means like I need
to buy another stack of HBM. There's not
really any way I can sort of uh I may I
make I can maybe crank up the frequency
on on on the on the pin speed. Um but
beyond that I just need to buy more
stacks of HBM. HBM is a big fraction of
the um sort of total cost of ownership
of of a chip. Um in in many cases it can
actually be more expensive than the the
logic die. Um
So, like and we're really up against the
limits of of of the physics on on the
memory bandwidth side. So, like next
generation HBMs like there's even
question of can we cool it? Do we need
to separate it from the logic die to be
able to cool it? Um big physical uh uh
challenges. Um whereas for logic uh
we
to some extent Moore's law is still
happening. It's a lot slower than it was
in the past, but there are improvements
generation over generation. And then
architecturally there's just big things
you can do to pack in um still another
factor of two, three, four more flops um
into logic dies. And so, uh there just
seems to be for the time being and for
the last few years like a lot more
headroom to cheaply increase flops.
Right. Let's talk about cooling here.
Like um I imagine with more and more
flops going into chips we're probably
looking at water cooling.
Yeah, for sure. Uh so, yeah. Um
Yeah, how how do you square with this
with like I don't know. Like it seems
significantly harder and more expensive
to build out the system now. Um how are
you sort of thinking of of that
trade-off relative to flops when it
comes to like sort of like the the total
cost of ownership here?
Yeah, so I mean, I think it really
depends on what's the right denominator,
right? So, if you look at the cost of a
system, like what is the cost of a rack?
That has been going up and up and up.
But the rack does like twice as much or
three times as much or something like
that. So, it's like the right
denominator is cost per flop, cost per
token per second, something like that.
Um
and uh
the reason you go to higher power is
that you can also go to higher clock
frequency on your chip. Um and so, for
the same square millimeters of silicon
you can get twice the performance or
three times the performance or something
like that. So, and and you don't pay
twice or three times as much on on the
on the cooling uh there. Um so, that
ends up being a net win. Um and I think
probably keeps pushing for a while.
I mean, I know this maybe sort of
harkens back to like the
Pentium era like pushing 4 GHz clock
speeds on CPUs, but there's sort of a a
difference there, which is that it's um
in those days it was like clock speed is
how you get the sequential time. Like
the number of sequential instructions um
to improve, whereas today it's how do
you get like more parallel uh throughput
out. And so, that is in some sense a
more um
uh you're not as much beating your head
against the wall to uh there. Like it's
actually productive. Yeah, I remember
like trying to overclock uh CPUs back in
the day and you have to put these like
crazy crazy liquid coolers on there and
Yeah, and just on the architecture side
like they had super deep pipelines. Like
I think the the extreme was like a
15-stage CPU pipeline, which means your
branch misprediction penalties 15
cycles. Um
Branch mispredict pallet penalties on
like AI chips are like can be hundreds
of clock cycles and it's fine cuz you
don't take branches that often. And so,
you can do like like
millions or billions of multiplies in in
that time and it's totally fine. On on
on sort of the architecture side I think
we should maybe go back and talk about
the the SRAM. Like what's what's what's
new here, right? Like um I think like
there's a lot of interest in sort of low
latency high IOPS chips now. Um
and like part of the MatX claim here is
that you can just like do that and also
deliver good throughput, right? Like
Let's talk about how.
Yeah, okay. So, um
So, firstly like SRAM is on every single
chip always. And so, like when we say
what is an SRAM chip? Like why why is uh
like Google's TPUs, Amazon's Trainium,
Nvidia, why they're not SRAM chips? Um
Firstly, SRAM means weights in SRAM. Uh
and so, that is what Groq and Cerebras
have been doing.
Um
and uh there is sort of a relationship
of in order to support weights in SRAM I
need
um
uh I need a combination of enough SRAM,
enough interconnect to support all the
tensor parallelism, expert parallelism
to get the data in and out um and the
how that relates to the number of flops
on the chip. So,
when we say an SRAM chip, we really mean
all of that entire package is
uh configured correctly so they can I
can um keep my weights long-term
resident in SRAM.
Um
and that genuinely just does give you a
lot better latency than than HBM. Um
latency of a model goes as really like
it's the time it takes to load the model
weights into the multipliers. Um and so,
that's just like number of parameters
divided by the bandwidth. SRAM bandwidth
is a hundred times uh higher than HBM
bandwidth. And so, you can get a lot
lower latency. Um you tend to get only
10 times lower latency, not a hundred
times lower, but uh ballpark you can get
uh about an order of magnitude better.
That's the SRAM side. Um the the reason
that Groq and Cerebras as standalone
products have struggled is that
uh
SRAM capacity is so small and um and so,
like your challenges are can I fit the
weights? Can I fit the KVs? Mhm.
Can I fit the weights? Uh that actually
works totally fine. Run a pipeline
across hundreds of chips, thousands of
chips. Um
Put a tiny fraction of the weights in
every chip. Um you can totally do that.
Uh you pay almost no penalty in in any
scaling term. You have to pay for the
interconnect for it. The interconnect
isn't that bad.
Um
uh and so, uh you can unroll these very
deep pipelines.
Can we do the same strategy for KVs? We
can't. So, the problem is that when when
you unroll uh KVs over this huge number
of chips, you don't actually get any net
saving because
uh
now your batch size has grown by the
pipeline depth. So, batch size is n
times larger. You've saved n times uh
capacity per chip, but that cancels out
and you actually don't get any saving at
all.
>> [snorts]
>> So, um SRAM basically as a result, KVs
in SRAM does not work. There's not
enough capacity. You need to put them in
HBM.
So, I think
what that ends up meaning is the um
you need a chip with enough SRAM that
you can do a weights long-term in in
SRAM, but then also put your KVs in HBM.
Um and so, we're seeing some signs of
that in the market already. The um
>> [clears throat]
>> This is how
uh Nvidia and Groq are starting to
deploy there um hybrid like put a Nvidia
rack next to a Groq rack. Um
Really I think the long term is that you
integrate it much more tightly and you
put uh a lot of SRAM and a big HBM um in
the same package. And that gives you
much power. Mhm. Yeah, like in in the
Nvidia and Groq case I guess these are
like two separate systems right now.
Like
I guess what's the trade-off here of
like I don't know. Sort of a
you're doing, right? Like a a chip that
just has has both a lot of SRAM and and
a lot of HBM.
Yeah, so I mean,
what it like sort of the trade-off is
you've put this I mean, for for
understandable reasons and it's a good
like it's a good sort of practical
measure to do what they've done. Um but
what it does is it puts this puts this
barrier in between. And so, I've got a
certain number of resources on on the
left and a certain number of resources
on the right.
And you're stuck with that split. And if
you want to move stuff from one side to
the other, like I want to move for
example some of my flops from the Nvidia
chip to the Groq chip or something like
that. Um
How do you do that? Like you're you're
stuck. You have to move uh the
computation there, which means you have
to move the uh interconnect there. And
and so, you have this interconnect
bottleneck then.
You can just tightly couple the HBM into
the SRAM if you design a a system for
that. Um and that gives you all of that
gives you the opportunity to move all of
the HBM bandwidth into SRAM. Um and that
actually gives you a lot of interesting
new opportunities. One example would be
uh that you can um do a a load of
something, typically a KV cache, um from
HBM into SRAM and then keep it in SRAM
for quite a long time. Uh but then bring
the next one in. And so, that's
uh just like this is sort of if you were
designing from first principles, that's
what you'd do. Right. Yeah. And in terms
of like what you're designing these
chips for, right? Let's talk a little
bit about that. Like
I think you're like being fairly
targeted in like what sort of models
you're trying to support. How are you
reasoning about this? How are you sort
of like thinking ahead to like when
these chips are are rolling out, like
what are people going to want to train
and and run? Yeah. Um so, I mean, the
the original vision was like uh the
needs of Frontier Labs. That is still
the vision. Um
And and and I think that mostly shows
shows up as very large models, very
large batch sizes. Um
Still low latency but large batch sizes.
Um I think it's maybe worth contrasting
that with
like
approaches that other chips have taken
in the past.
One of the big things was like saying
can we do like batch size one, can we do
small models like convolutions or things
like that, things with small channel
counts.
I have some past experiences working on
such chips as well.
One of the challenges there is that you
spend a huge amount of the chip, I mean
like actually just thinking time in how
you design the chip but as well as
area and silicon on the chip supporting
these small models well and it's just a
much harder problem. You have to figure
out how to take like a small convolution
kernel and replicate it over all of your
chip or and then solve the data movement
problems inside the chip that are
associated with that.
Or
manage my low batch size and figure out
how to extract all of the possible
parallelism from from from a single user
rather than extracting parallelism from
just like I've got 10,000 users in
concurrently.
So that was a whole bunch of no we don't
want to do that stuff.
Nvidia has always been supporting that
stuff as as well as they can. A lot of
the 2017 era of startups like did it put
a lot of the innovation into that
problem and we said no no thank you not
to that.
We are going to have the whole chip
focusing on one
sort of coherent thing at a time.
And rely on the fact that we have enough
work to do, large enough matrices,
enough large enough batch sizes that we
can have a little chip doing that one
thing at a time. That leads to a much
simpler design.
We then spend some of that
simplicity
to then like use our innovation budget
on
okay can we support attention with this
like small attention head size really
efficiently for example.
So so overall I think that ended up
being
LLMs in the way we see them now and and
evolving.
I think those are all the sort of the
qualitative architectural sides of it
and then the product choices are
low latency is like it's just a free
like it's a free idea that
needs to be put into the right product
which is SRAM and HBM and then put a
huge amount of flops in because like
flops is one of the most valuable
resources. Yeah.
And and so like
with all these with all these flops like
how how are you thinking about like I
don't know like how are people going to
use these flops?
I you have an ML team that thinks about
things like this. Let's let's chat about
like some of the work they're doing. So
I mean let's start with
how do you use those flops at least in
the first place. So training prefill
decode training and prefill are
compute limited. You can always apply
more flops there it's very pretty
straightforward.
Um
The sticker is is decode.
The sort of the common
concern or hesitation is
decode is entirely HBM bandwidth
limited. There's nothing you can do so
like don't don't try to apply more flops
there. There's a few angles to say that
that might be
wrong or at least short-sighted.
Um
Maybe one of the most fundamental is
like
if you've got a chip where the flops are
sitting idle surely there must be
somewhere you can figure out how to use
them productively.
And I I know it's kind of a little glib
because like
um
like let's talk about the specific ways
rather than just like abstractly what
the what the what they could be.
But there's a big part of
like I think like I'm sure many many of
the labs in general are going to be
working on on answering this exact
problem but
we have some opinions on like maybe it's
actually existential dramatics as well
and so
like thinking about what that might look
like a few years from now. That's a big
part of what our ML team does.
So to break down that problem like the
in in a model you have the attention
layer and the feedforward network layer
or the MoE layer.
You can always throw more flops at
feedforward network MoE.
Just make it bigger,
make it less sparse,
run it a few times in a row, all kinds
of things like that.
What is the most productive way to to
make those changes and actually realize
that in terms of model quality? And at
some point like if you can make that big
enough it'll like you should get to a
balance point between
memory bandwidth and and flops.
The other side of that so that's make
the MoE bigger. The other side of that
is make the attention smaller. So
there's so many things in the literature
for that. Generally general ideas that
are well established are like
alternating long and short context,
reusing KB caches over consecutive
layers, using fewer KB heads,
and then maybe things like multi-head
latent attention where you sort of
compress the heads down and then grow
them up.
And then maybe even like
a bigger hammer than all of that is to
access the KB cache sparsely.
So a range of all of those things there
are so many ideas to grapple with there
and like what is the right way to think
about that? One of the things we we do
on our ML team is just to
try and understand the space and then
quantify what is the exchange rate
between HBM bandwidth and
and and flops. So
how is there even an exchange rate
there? Really that's what saying is like
let's say I want to get 1% improvement
in
in model quality in some sense. So like
as if you know as if I had double the
size of my model something like that. So
um
we know how to do that on flops.
Keep doubling the size of the model
until the quality is better. How many
doublings of HBM bandwidth do I need to
get the equivalent?
Uh
And so like just a starting point is
just measure that and understand where
it's at.
Really interesting problem like
there's many difficult ways to measure.
Do you have to be very sensitive to how
you measure it right because
simple ways of measuring like loss for
example if you just look at the impact
on loss it'll say actually you know just
like have short context of 64 tokens
never attend beyond that and just have a
massive model and that actually is what
the like that'll optimize the loss for
you know per cost in in some sense.
So you know some of what we spend some
time being maybe we can be a little bit
more sophisticated about how you measure
quality and like actually sort of up
weight long context
like aspects of quality that show up in
long context more
in our models. Yeah.
Like sort of along that line one one
axis in which in which models have
changed a lot and hardware has changed a
lot is in like numerics right? Like I
think everyone is sort of pushing
towards like lower and and lower bit
representations. How are you thinking
about numerics? Like what what will the
matics chips support and and like how
are you thinking around sort of the ML
consequences of your numerics scheme
here? I mean numerics has been the
single biggest
sort of
actual improvement in flops per watt of
of anything like anyone has done over
the last 10 years. It's it's always been
that. So Nvidia has been having the
precision multiple times starting at 32
16 8 4.
And I think it's with good reason. The
the reason it I mean empirically the
results are good. If I you know going
all the way from 32-bit to 8-bit like it
was almost a free lunch. You you have
the precision. There's zero loss in
quality. Like like as long as you get
the recipe right you don't even have to
increase the number of parameters or
anything. It's it's just like free lunch
totally.
We've gone past that like
leadingly obvious like free lunch thing
and and now it's like when you go from
8-bit to 4-bit
you do lose quality but
uh
but not too much and so for example
maybe I have to add 50% more parameters
to keep the quality the same but on
Nvidia I get a three times speed up
going from 8-bit to 4-bit and so
um
uh twice the parameters three times
speed up it's isn't a two times speed
up. Like we we see this trend.
We really want to lean into it. We
One of the challenges is kind of to meet
the customer where they are in I mean
both the customer and the research where
it is
and I think there's always the challenge
with hardware because the hardware
timelines are so much longer than
than ML research timelines.
If you kind of try and ask the question
of where are people designing models for
today maybe the answer is FP8. That that
is much too backwards looking. So so you
have to be a little bit old in in in
your bets on numerics but then you also
have to figure out how to
manage the risk that you that that your
prediction is wrong. So
without going into specifics some of
what we do there is
our ML team has done amazing research on
on actually what numerics we we feel we
can trust and I I think at this point we
have as far as I know
from our point of view of all things
considered of cost and flexibility and
we have a great numerics solution in our
chip.
Our team has like validated every sort
of all of that and seen we can train
train models. We know what the quality
loss is there and when considering
quality versus speed it's it's really
attractive.
Like one of the other aspects that shows
up here is like because of the
uncertainty of prediction like
how do we manage the sort of the tail
risks of like maybe
maybe models will turn out worse than we
thought or maybe models will turn out
better than we thought in in the
response to recession and so we've got
some nice ideas there too.
Great. And and something interesting to
me is that like you're one of the few
sort of newer [clears throat] chip
companies that are targeting both
training and inference models right?
Like why why make this choice? I mean
like on the surface it seems that like
inference is sort of like the easy
obvious choice for this both from like a
software perspective and also just like
from a from like thinking about the
hardware.
Do you want to talk a bit about like why
why make this choice to do both training
and inference here? Yeah so I mean like
there's one angle is the historical
angle which is like to say
why did all of those chips in 2017
choose to do inference only? And that
was a genuinely simpler problem than
training because no interconnect
actually was a big thing. Like you could
make a single chip like without any
interconnect it can run like a LSTM of
the day or a convolution of the day.
It's like 500 million parameters fits in
the memory of one chip. Like single chip
solution really really easy to do.
That is not the case at all today right?
Like we're running inferences on
hundreds of chips or more um
even for inference. And so
the inference chips that anyone makes
today have to be rack scale systems um
or bigger um
and you've bitten off already most of
the complexity that shows up, the system
complexity for a training solution, too.
So, the delta from that to a training
solution is
maybe for training you want scale up
solution. Maybe for inference you want
that, too, especially if you're doing
weights and Astra and you need very
large uh um connectivity domains.
Um
and then
what what else is there in the delta? Um
maybe you want a different set of
precisions for training. Um sometimes
training is done at higher precision.
Sometimes there are other tricks that
apply in training and not inference uh
for for precision. Um
that delta is also pretty small in
reality. Um
And then and then training has transpose
operations, I guess is the other one.
And so um
but all of these things are kind of
relatively small in in terms of uh
the
actual impact on on your chip design. Um
and so
I mean, you have to make a prediction
about how much of the market will be
training, but I think probably at least
30%. Probably not 50% because there's
this RL component that is uh
substantially inference, too.
But for, you know, a 5% increase in your
development effort, you can you can get
another like
uh 1/3 of the market, which is a pretty
attractive place to be. So, uh I think
that's the like logical calculus that
was behind it. Um
This is borne out by
the current incumbents are all both
training and inference chips in Nvidia,
Google, Amazon. Um
uh as well as like there's just this
story of like as a customer point of
view, you get this optionality of I can
buy a fleet for inference, but I then
get the possibility of running training
on it as well. Um and so the, you know,
a like especially as a customer I'm I'm
thinking I'm going to be committed to
these chips for 3 years 2 years I don't
from now I don't know what the world's
going to look like could be totally
different. And so getting a bit of
optionality there is uh is also like in
this in this aspect is
is a nice bonus feature, I think. Yeah,
that makes sense. The the timeline here
sort of seems pretty central to like a
lot of the decisions being made, right?
So, like I don't know, let's talk about
timeline. Like if I wanted to start
making a chip right now, right? Like I
start the design process now. Like when
when do I get my chip? Like when do I
have it in a system in a in a data
center? Yeah, so like I I have an idea
for a chip and I want to do like the
architecture and then the RTL to TV and
uh and then tape out and and so on. Um
Development times from like product idea
to uh to tape out are typically several
years. Um that's probably accelerating
with AI. Um
uh
Not as much as in as in software because
a big part because of risk management
that um
redoing a tape out I mean the tape out
is not that exp- that expensive. It is
only $30 even if I much more than that
on model runs these days. Um but but
really like the cost of a respin is not
just the tape out, but then also like
you've deployed billions of dollars
chips in the field if you have um and so
so there's there's a whole
like in reality there's something on the
order of a few billion dollars of like
total
uh project at stake there that that
causes you to be still more conservative
in hardware than in software.
Um and I think that sort of back
propagates to
uh
the success of uh of AI as applied to
chips has not been as good to date as as
applied to software. Um I'm sure that's
going to like improve over time, but uh
Where where where do you see this like
accelerating things the most? Like is it
I don't know,
are the models like fairly good at
writing Verilog? Is it is it something
else in the stack?
>> Yeah, the um I mean most of the stack is
software. So, like or like is shaped
like software development. So, uh so
they're pretty good at writing Verilog.
Um they're
uh which is a lot of the development. Uh
they, you know, they can also do design
verification. There's this question of
like, okay, they've done that. You trust
it. You trust the coverage. Maybe you
should like uh review it somewhat
yourself as well. Um
But um I think they're pretty good
there. Um
We haven't seen them be so good on the
product and architecture side yet. Um I
think that also maybe requires different
workflows for how you do product and
architecture. Um but like a lot of I
think maybe more so in in hardware than
what I've seen in software, there's a
lot more um work done sort of the whole
model is more waterfall than than what
you see in software typically. And so
there's a lot more work done um prior to
writing code. So, writing architecture
docs um
uh modeling performance out and so on.
Um
The any any time where it's modeling
performance, you can do that in Python.
Models will do a pretty good job of
that. But uh but sort of reasoning
through a a lot of the other stuff, I
think there's there's a component there
that is
more shaped like prose than than code.
Um and so that's that's not
to date not such a a great fit. Um And
then there's also an another aspect
which is not at all shaped like code.
Physical design is like uh
is based in a in a GUI and you're like
um
there's actually a lot of physical work
and then slow iteration times where you
do a placement run index a week or 2
weeks or something like that. Um
uh and so not so well adapted to the
kind of flows that we have today. Um I
don't know, I think all of this can get
a lot faster, but like sort of if you
look at what is the um
limiting factor there, there is still
the uh there's I don't know, a year year
and a half 2 years from from tape out to
production deployment, which is like
entire physical supply chain and and
tape out and so on.
In terms of like sort of the the the
tools being relatively slow and the
iteration iteration times being long,
right? Like at what point do you just go
and, you know, rewrite the stack on the
on these things, right? Like I don't
know, it's become a lot easier to I mean
the stack is just software, right? And
so like Yeah. At what point do you just
go in and say like we're just going to
rewrite the stack here and and make
things much faster and and like I don't
know, get better iteration times. Are
are people doing this already? Yeah, I
think it's an interesting question. Um
so, I mean, to be clear about that
stack, that stack is the EDA tool stack
which is produced by so EDA electronic
design automation. Um
It's primarily produced by Cadence and
Synopsys. Um and the reason those tools
are so expensive firstly is because they
embody in them the um the trust me I
I've done the tape outs and when I when
I give you a design that I say will meet
TSMC's like design rule checks and uh
will will meet timing and won't uh like
won't have electrical interference
between all of the wires. All of these
yucky physical problems that we don't
want to deal with. Um
like that's why we pay them the the
money for that. Um uh
So, uh like that is quite a different um
style of work than at least what we as a
fabless semiconductor company do. Um I I
sure hope either like Synopsys and
Cadence are are doing this uh rewriting
themselves or and I'm sure there's
probably a bunch of startups as well
doing that as well. Um but there is um
sort of some painful like decades of
experience of what what are all the
things that can go wrong in making sure
you you um you meet all of the design
rules um that uh that is maybe something
of a bit of a barrier to entry or at
least like um
you're going to have to like waste a few
hundred million dollars in in in bad
tape outs before you you get that
experience. Yeah.
Expensive. Yeah.
Yeah. And then like my impression is
that uh both like allocation for wafers
and then HBM are becoming increasingly
scarce. Like A like I don't know, what
does that look like today, right? And B
like how do you design a chip um for
this knowing that like I don't know,
like some of the things you may have
banked on are potentially hard to come
by or much more expensive than you
initially anticipated. Yeah, I mean, the
Yeah, I don't know, it's kind of weird,
right? Like you you can maybe sign a
contract with one of your vendors and
say, well, I, you know, will agree to
logic dies at this price, but then like
ultimately that might the supply might
not exist. And so you've agreed to a
price that like
like just like the the supply and demand
uh just doesn't intersect and and we'll
have to renegotiate the price in in the
future. So, there is that possibility
and that unfortunately exists with logic
dies and and memory dies as well. Um To
some extent where uh I mean, what are
the kinds of moves you can make in this
place? Um the the most fundamental thing
is just to
um
to have better economics there. So, uh
the if you can get better performance
out of every square millimeter of
silicon, that means you can you can pay
more than your competition for for a
wafer um
when you're like at the uh if if you're
selling at cost, basically. So, if
you're selling at cost uh um
we can sustain um higher costs than than
say our competition because we get more
value out of the every square millimeter
of silicon. Um likewise for for HBM
bandwidth. Um if you can put every byte
per second of HBM bandwidth to more
productive use than then you can outbid
your competitors while still, you know,
um being price performance uh parity.
Um So, that I think is the
like first principles uh reasons that
um
we think we can have a sustaining
advantage here. Um then there's the just
like the day-to-day uh
um business side of signing the right
deals and and and forming the right
partners. And I think uh
I mean, without going into too much
specifics, I think making sure you have
the right partnerships and and uh and
getting close to some of the big players
is is important there.
And in terms of sort of the overall
supply here, like I don't know, how are
things looking going forward? Like are
is is HBM sort of hard to come by now or
>> Yeah, no, HBM probably is. Logic wafers
a little bit um
uh and and then um
uh advanced packaging is also hard to
come by. The whole the whole ecosystem
is very scarce, but uh but I think like
everyone feels this across the whole
supply chain. Yeah. Yeah, sort sort of
going back to like the the, you know,
you can if you can get more like flops
or performance per square millimeter,
like you can have better pricing. Like
how how do you see sort of pricing and
and margins going forward, right? Like I
think for the last couple of years like
Nvidia has been able to like sustain
these insane margins because there's
been very little competition and I think
this is like starting to change, right?
So, like how are how are you sort of
reasoning about this in terms of like I
don't know, like how do you price a chip
in a world where there's like a couple
of different chips that are potentially,
you know, able to be used for training
and inference effectively? Yeah, so I
mean, our own pricing strategy, I mean,
what
we're selling to maybe five different
customers in in the world. So like we we
don't really need to put our price on
the website. We're like we're going to
we're just going to negotiate it with
with with
end customers.
Um
Uh so how would you price your strategy?
Ultimately, we're going to we'll we'll
negotiate it. Um when it gets to the
point where we're like being asked to
sell at cost, like we we have to say no,
sorry. Um but uh
um
So like uh but like zooming out and
saying um how would you expect the
industry to to react in in both a like a
place where there's not a lot of
competition, you should be able to
charge high margins. Um and then as
there is more competition, the um the
margins should in general come down. So
I I think that will be the case over the
next few years. Um
The I mean, both in the current
incumbents, like uh Nvidia, Google,
Amazon, um
uh Google being willing to sell outside
of its own data centers, which we've
seen some instances of. Um More more of
Google's traditional competitors buying
Google's chips, um rather than Nvidia's
or in in conjunction with Nvidia's. Um
uh Open AI buying AMD chips. All of that
is like signs that even even among the
traditional chips, uh margins are coming
down. Um and we sort of see that with
some of the uh deals where Nvidia is um
is not discounting the chips on a cash
basis, but maybe on a like there's some
equity deal that that effectively
functions as a discount. But it looks
better on Yeah, the accounting
department.
>> Yes. Uh
um so I think margins are coming down.
Um
The
like
As a startup, we we have to plan for
from our perspective the worst, which is
that like we had we we we sell at cost
plus 1% or something like that. Um
The
I don't think we will sell for that low
of a price. I think we'll sell it like
way more than that. Um The the price
that we expect to be forced to is price
performance parity with with with with
the best competitor. Um and we we will
be very happy at that point. Right. And
in that case, like performance is now is
now sort of the the selling point,
right? And so like And and and so like I
don't know like like why why Matics,
right? Like why why Matics sort of went
on this on this axis versus I guess like
the the potentially many competitors
that'll that'll be out there. So
performance. Um There's throughput and
latency. Um Latency the latency bar
historically has been just the latency
get out of get out of HBM. It takes 20
milliseconds to read all of HBM on most
generations of HBM. Like it gets like
that's has been remarkably stable from
like HBM1 through HBM4. Um which is
really just a function of you get a
bandwidth increase, but you also get a
capacity increase. And so
uh
that 20 milliseconds has essentially set
what has been typically the the latency
of a of a inference forward pass. And so
uh
you you can do speculative coding
because you get a bit of an advantage
over that, but uh
ballpark uh HBM-based systems generally
see a few hundred uh OTBS, uh which is
coming from this uh this drain time of
HBM.
That um that table stakes is probably
going to become like more like a
millisecond rather than 20 milliseconds.
So thousandish. One to 2,000 OTBS. Um
Uh because of I think general industry
industry switch over the next few years
to
um weights in SRAM.
Um
I don't see much path for going
substantially below that um in the short
term.
Um
It really depends on model sizes. Things
you can do with smaller models,
especially very dense models. There
there are tricks that you can go uh
below that. Tellus has put out a nice
demo, which is like uh about an order of
magnitude better than that, but that
like relied on a very particular sweet
spot of not a sparse model, very small
model, so that you can fit in one chip
the whole model. Um but once you sort of
fall out of that sweet spot, you you
like I think it'll generally go back to
about the millisecond uh per forward
pass.
Um So performance uh on the latency
aspect, that is to say, I think
there is a new table stakes. Matics hits
that. Probably a few other companies
will hit it more and more well over
time. Um uh I think that will sort of be
end up being the new sort of table
stakes and neutral point.
From that neutral point, then the
question is do you win on throughput?
That comes down to really two things. Um
What is the flops you're getting out or
flops per square millimeter or flops per
dollar? Um
as well as what is your ability to
support like long context uh well and
manage the
KB cache load times.
So uh we'll do the flops first. Um so
uh Matics has the most flops per square
millimeter of any announced product um
by a pretty good margin. Um
This is um
coming from from some of the work we've
done in numerics. It's also coming from
uh just some of the architectural work
we've done to uh
avoid a lot of the overheads of like
communication inside the chip, as well
as um too much flexibility that you see
in other solutions. Um this is sort of
what I was saying about
um overheads from like supporting
convolutions or low batch size things.
Like if you decide not to do those
things, you can you can make a
substantially simpler architecture.
Um
All of that together ends up meaning
that we have a lot better flops.
Um
And then on the
uh KB cache side, this is really
hybrid
weights in SRAM, KBs in HBM, uh and
really the model architecture the
principle that you have in mind there is
um sparse attention. So not fetching all
of KBs every time, but fetching a small
subset of the KBs every time. Th- That
that is sort of how you make uh like
achieve high throughput uh
uh even though your weights are in SRAM.
So uh if if you do not have this HBM
available, you would be forced into a
low batch size in order to fit all of
the KBs. Um And a low batch size uh
limits the amount of performance you can
get or the amount of throughput you can
get.
And so like I don't know, we've kind of
talked about like, you know, the the
sort of hardware approaches the
different chips have taken over the last
couple years. There's like the SRAM-only
ones, there's like the the more
traditional like
HBM-first ones and then sort of like
what Matics is doing. Let's talk about
software. Um yeah. To to me it seems
like most the sort of uh chip companies
in the in the last sort of 10 years have
tried to build out a full stack, right?
Where like I don't know, you you write
some JAX or or PyTorch and and you get
something running on the the model. This
is not the approach you're you're trying
to take here. Yeah.
>> Um Let's talk about why.
So what are the successes of this
approach? Um I think Google has been the
clear success. Uh Google had had a new
hardware that was not a GPU um and they
um made JAX work really well on it. Um
uh and so at least like take that as a
case study in my own experiences of like
being at Google and writing JAX code,
it's pretty productive. You can get to
maybe good like 50% MFU or so uh writing
sort of straight-up JAX without like at
the high level, JAX XLA.
Uh 50% is pretty good performance, but
like you might hope for 70%, 90% if you
can.
To get that last mile, um it seems to
always be the case in practice that you
you're going to want to write custom
kernels.
Um it's just like I think it's a reality
that like if you try and teach a
compiler how to do good optimizations,
it is so much work because you have to
think, well, a compiler could
get any kind of input at all. And so the
specific optimization that I know how to
do in this specific case,
now I have to generalize and say, well,
I could get a thousand different cases
and I have to figure out how to do the
optimization in all of these cases. So
just as a sort of
um an engineering problem of
am I more productive solving the
optimization in in one case versus a
thousand cases? Like obviously in one
case it's it's an easier problem. So
So that incentive pushes you towards
wanting to write custom kernels for for
most of your model over time.
Um and from what I can see, that is uh
that is the reality of how it has borne
out in the labs. So um the labs uh have
large uh people teams of people writing
custom kernels for the platforms they're
they're on. Um and
uh and I think for ultimately for the
for this reason, um it is worth spending
the human time to uh to make the model
cheaper. And uh and you can get pretty
big wins there.
Um
So from our perspective, let's lean into
that. Uh if you know that your customers
are going to be writing custom kernels,
for 10%
That's also nice for us because it says,
okay, we're not going to have to spend a
huge amount of time developing a
compiler that uh that's not going to be
so useful.
Um I think all of this is predicated on
sophisticated users. Um This strategy
would not work at all for um if we're
trying to sell to a small shop that has
only like 10 engineers or something like
that because they they need they need
the productivity there more than more
than the the the performance. Yeah. I
guess the one place where to me it it
seems that this like approach runs into
some headwinds is like when you're doing
sort of like research and like like
training research um type workloads,
right? Like what what are your thoughts
on that? Like is this something that
you're just sort of not targeting for
now or like is there sort of a plan in
the future to to address that sort of
use case where like flexibility is is is
useful, right? And like um writing you
know, the entire model as kernels is is
potentially hard. Yeah. Um so I mean, I
think the simplest answer is for now
that's not a main focus for us. Um
uh
like we are not trying to say to a lab,
you will we will be 100% of your chips.
We're happy to be
50%, 75%. That would be a lot of
business to have. Happy to be 10% as
well. I I think that leaves a lot of
room to say uh you do your um research
on on on a platform that's optimized for
um flexibility and productivity. Um and
then when you're doing uh switching to
like uh hero runs or like starting to
scale up your model to prepare for a
hero run, or then when you've trained
your model and you want to deploy it, uh
that's where you switch to a different
um
uh to a different platform like Matics.
Um maybe as a slightly hot take, I kind
of
like
I believe this is not universally the
case, but I think um this is a
reasonable approach to have even if
you're on one platform, in fact. That uh
maybe you should just have a separate
code base for uh research and
production. Have them as two separate
code bases
even if both of them are going to be on
on GPUs or Google or something like
that. Um just from the point of view of
like
I'm optimizing for a very different set
of constraints here than than for here.
And like why would I force them to be
the same thing?
I might force them to be the same thing
so I can do a transfer like a transfer
from research to production really
effectively. Um that is a valid goal to
have. But other goals you might also
have are can I have my researchers be
extremely productive and not by the same
like same set of constraints which is
that I want production to be like very
high
and and
bandwidth utilization as well. So like
don't necessarily don't over couple
together the two different use cases you
have. Um
which I think it plays in software but
like more strongly it also plays in
hardware. Right. It's also harder to
switch back and forth on hardware for
that, right?
Yeah, that that that that makes sense to
me. Um
And then I guess like what what is this
like like let's say I want to write my
model on on an Amatic's chip, right?
Like what what does this look like? Is
it something It's obviously not
something like JAX but like is it
something like Triton? Is it something
lower level? Are you going to give me
your ISA? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um
We'll we'll give you our ISA wrapped in
a Python DSL. Um Uh I think that's sort
of it gives
you as a customer gives you what you
want from the point of view of I want to
know the instructions that are running
so I can debug if the performance is not
as good as I want. I understand why. I
expect that I mean in our own workflows
we look at
at the instruction level of what are the
ALUs I have? What is the mapping of my
instruction to those ALUs? Are there
like resource bubbles in here? And I
and you know people writing kernels are
are going to be doing the same thing. So
exposing the ISA pretty closely is is
um
uh it's just like lets you use it where
they want. I think like
that is the lowest level of what we do.
Sort of aspirations for future I think
the aspiration for future is more of a
Triton or Palace like thing. That is a
pretty nice level of abstraction I think
the teams that at
at OpenAI and Google did a really good
job there
of
like you don't want something too high
level. The risk of going too high level
is that you're having the computer make
decisions like the compiler make
decisions that
you could have made better yourself. Um
and so
like don't hand over the keys to the
kingdom.
Um But at the same time you do want the
compiler to make decisions that are not
very interesting for you to make and a
computer can make better. And so I think
uh Triton and Palace did a pretty good
job with that. The The The user is
making decisions on
definitely HBM transfers
transfers over interconnect
and even like loop order which are like
those are the most important decisions
to make. You should totally make them by
hand. Um and then but then they had it
over to the compiler the sort of
short-term decisions of SRAM loads and
stores and and sort of inner loop order.
Um I think
so that theme of like picking where to
make those decisions and go a little
high level is nice.
Um
To some extent it is still a little too
high level because
it's appropriate for chips like TPUs and
GPUs where
um SRAM bandwidth is abundant or L1
cache bandwidth is abundant
but that's actually leaving some
performance on the table or silicon area
on the table. And so
if you want to recover that performance
as well then it sort of pushes you to
maybe a slightly lower level of
abstraction still. Mhm. Yeah.
We've we've talked about TPUs in in
Google a lot. Um You've spent a lot of
time at Google. Yeah. What what did you
do there? What what what did you you
know? Yeah. So I um
So I was at Google for about a decade. I
I started
as a as a web developer
which is just like in 2012 what you
would do. Um
I love it. Did you make the Amatic's
website?
I I made an early version of the
Amatic's website. When it when it looked
really ugly I made it. Like
my making it
things look nice was never my area
really my area but one of the things I
cared about a lot with the Amatic's
website is like as a company we make
things really efficient and we should
have the same attention to detail with
with the website.
I you know the the original version of
the Amatic's website was about 5 or 10
kilobytes. Like it loads really fast. No
no no like no redundant requests. All
all loads in one request. Loads very
fast. So yeah and I put some work into
something. I I It's it's maybe a little
obsessive but it like it's it's the kind
of thing I like to do.
So I yeah I spent like maybe 5 years
doing that at Google.
And then
and then I I wanted to switch into some
of the machine learning teams and so I
did
Originally I did some software work on
large scale logistic regression which is
like a one layer neural network but that
was before
the the neural network revolution.
Um and then as that revolution started
to happen I I moved over to a
to a neural net chip team. So this was
actually a competitor to the TPUs. Um
There's some sort of a little bit of
shared lineage. Jonathan Ross from Grok
was on that project for a very short
amount of time before he went to start
Grok. Um
and then and then most recently after
working on chips I moved to the LM team.
So I was on Brain.
Uh
I helped train Google Palm
and then I wrote the inference stack for
Palm as well. And so that was
like very very hands-on with LLMs there.
Yeah.
And and I guess like now at Amatic's,
right? Like I mean I'm sure you know you
have a lot of sort of non-technical work
that you have to get to but like when
when you do have sort of when you do a
technical work like what do you spend
your time on? Like what Yeah, like what
are what are you spending your time on?
Currently the places that I'm closest to
are the the ML research and and the
architecture. Um
Uh in the very early days of Amatic's I
was also pretty deep in the
in some of the software stack but since
then it's been rewritten and much better
by by people who have more attention and
and and experience than I do on that.
But I like I think it's so important for
a hardware company to be very close to
the ML research as in both to directly
inform our product our entire numeric
stack was was
a result of our ML research.
But then also to uh have as good of a
crystal ball as we can for where models
are going. Um
and so
I think I think the work that the team
does there is really cool and exciting.
On and then on the architecture side
I think architecture is sort of the
heart obviously of a company like this.
And so
there's like that ranges from the like
the sort of coarse-grained thing of like
how do you organize the chip? How do you
connect all of the cores of the chip
together?
Lots of interesting things you can do
there. But then it goes down into like
even to the microarchitecture level like
one of the examples is like um
the kinds of co-design you can do where
you say well um there are these
standards for how you do rounding. Round
to nearest ties go to to the nearest
even is like one of the IEEE standards.
Um but it's really overkill.
And so if you like simultaneously pay
attention to the microarchitecture of
what does a circuit for that rounding
look like? Um and then at the same time
can I prove with my ML
modeling
work that I could do a cheaper circuit.
Like the the marriage of the
microarchitecture and and and the ML
model I think is a really
sort of attractive opportunity for for
co-design. Mhm. Yeah. On the on the sort
of co-design front, right? Like
I mean some some competitors, right?
Like I don't know OpenAI is making their
own chip. And and and so like
as as sort of external to a to a lab and
like obviously Google, you know, does
both their own hardware and and their
own models. And so like how are how are
you sort of trying to co-design for
something that you, you know, don't know
the exact shape of and and still sort of
beat out your competitors on that? Yeah.
And and I think one aspect of this is
the more general thing of like is
are the advantages of vertical
integration? How So
there are advantages of vertical
integration. You get more information
about what your workload is.
And then compare that to the advantages
of having like
multiple customer customers chip
customers buying from a single chip
vendor. There are advantages to
centralization as well. And so like
long-term there's a question of which
one which of those paradigms wins.
Um
the
So just to spell that out historically
Nvidia has won. Uh like the um you know,
they are selling to multiple different
buyers and so they can aggregate the
research dollars into into one product.
Whereas when there are multiple
different buyers those research dollars
have to be spent sort of duplicately
and you can't do as much research. I
think that is that is a reason to to
think that actually a a standalone
company like Amatic's could succeed
even despite if for example OpenAI
developing their own chips. Um
In the short term how do we do co-design
um when when we're not when we don't
have this information? We have to do the
best job we can of getting information
of what models are.
Um
It was easier in 2022 when people
published all the models.
They stopped doing that in '22. Maybe
OpenAI and Anthropic stopped that maybe
in '21 a little bit earlier. But
but at this point everyone has stopped
except for the the Chinese labs.
So
uh
Open source as a source of information
is still reasonably good especially
coming from DeepMind. They've uh
put a lot of really informative papers
out. To some extent you can talk to
customers. You can't get a lot there
because customers really value their own
IP.
But you can you can get a little bit.
And then you have to do your best job of
covering the distribution of likely
outcomes. So like maybe the 80%
central part of the distribution and
ignore the 10% 20% tails.
Um
So
that is sort of what we do. We like a
way to think about it is we look at the
primitives that are used in neural nets.
So obviously matrix multiplication uh
standards like floating point vector
operations to do all the common set of
non-linear functions.
And then there's some things that you
need for sparsity and then maybe some
different routing modes for
inference and training. Um
There is that set of primitives. That
set of primitives as a class has been
extremely stable over the last 5 10
years in fact of neural nets. And so
betting on the primitives uh is actually
a pretty safe place to be. And I think
it's very unlikely that
model changes a year or two years from
now are going to move outside of that
set of primitives. It's just because
like it's kind of the intersection of
what what is efficient on hardware or in
physics, what is efficient in physics,
as well as what is efficient for
gradient descent. And so so
like that is a starting place that gives
us sort of a um
a
foundation of stability.
Kinds of things we do for for actual
co-design is or or like using knowledge
about models is um what is the what is
the ratio of those resources, how much
we put in.
Um
And and that becomes a hard question
when it's
when it's a costly decision of how much
of this resource versus that resource.
So how much interconnect is is a pretty
costly decision because it's quite
expensive. In other places it's not so
costly, like how much
sorting throughput is actually a pretty
like it's pretty cheap to provision, so
you can we can over provision that.
Um so that's sort of our methodology in
general. Um
the
Where this ends up is that
uh
the information advantage or
disadvantage um like we think we have a
pretty good crystal ball. Is is
ultimately
I think that that is a place of
differentiation for us. We think we have
a better crystal ball than than many. Um
and how can that even be the case when
you're comparing to a lab that has their
own like internal folks? Um
To put it bluntly, it's uh
the even when you talk to the
researchers they don't know what is
going to be the case in three years. And
so like you can talk to the researchers
all you want, they can tell you what
they're doing today, but if you're
trying to predict two or three years out
you still need to make your own
prediction. And so we think we can do a
good job with that. Mhm. And this is
flowing from sort of the the numerics
and and ML work you're doing while while
designing this chip. Yeah, as well as
just like um like having seen some of
the like longer term history of of of of
of the development of neural nets over
time. Mhm. Are [clears throat] you
you're you're the crystal ball here? Um
Uh
to a large extent, yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> Um I mean
uh
we
There's a lot of folks on the team. We
talk a lot to the ML team. Um and then
the architecture team is also
gets quite close to the ML research as
well. And so I think um
like considering all of those things in
mind, uh that's that we do the best job
we can there. We've sort of touched on
this, I think we just did in this past
conversation, but like let's let's talk
a bit about interconnect. Um like what
does your interconnect look like? Like
how is it different from what's out
there right now? And like like how does
this play into sort of the the
trade-offs you're making here and then
in terms of just sort of maximizing your
flops and and making things as simple as
possible.
Yeah, um
so where is interconnect
where is it expensive, what is it used
for? So um
uh you need enough interconnect.
Primarily primarily it's driven by
you need enough interconnect to get over
a certain bar of something. Um
That bar is actually different for
HBM-based chips and SRAM-based chips. Um
the traditional bar on HBM-based chips
is I want to do enough um internal
parallelism within a layer, so tensor
parallelism or expert parallelism. I
need to do enough of that in order to
get my latency down. Um at just to some
amount. Um and so like you then look how
much of that I need to do, how much
compute throughput do I have. Um
uh and then how much HBM bandwidth do I
have and and form form a decision there.
The bar for SRAM is actually phrased
slightly differently. It is a
I want to stick my weights in SRAM and
then uh I need to be able to like so
that means I can only do a certain
amount of computation before I run out
of SRAM and need to move to the next
chip. And so I need enough interconnect
that in that short amount of time I can
get the the the activations in and out.
Um
uh
But that actually does give give you a
relatively clear threshold for how much
interconnect you want. You have to
couple that with some predictions about
neural architecture um in terms of
um it's actually not too sensitive to
the size of a model, but it's it is
sensitive to some of the other hyper
parameters of a model. Um so there is
some amount of prediction that goes on
there.
What we have done on interconnect is
um provisioned a lot of it, for sure. Um
the the logic die cost of that is
actually um
not too bad. Uh I mean it is one of the
big ticket items like big ticket items
on a logic die are interconnect, SRAM,
and compute. Um and so it's it is up
there, but it's not it's not a it
doesn't balloon out of control. The
other cost is like the cables and the
power cost. And again it is a big ticket
item there, but it's not it's not out of
control. Um
the So so we have provisioned a lot
there. One of the things that is sort of
different is that um
a side benefit and we're going into too
much details, a side benefit of
weights in SRAM is actually it allows
you to um use your interconnect without
also using up HBM bandwidth, which is a
shocking thing, but
we're able to do that. And so like push
the interconnect performance higher than
than for example some of the incumbents
are able to um for that reason. So
that is not really talking about any of
the numbers or the topology of what we
do, but
we have a lot of interconnect. Um
uh
We've picked a what we think is a pretty
good topology as well. Um it is
different than some of the previous uh
topologies.
Um
Uh I think this is a point of innovation
for us. The kinds of considerations when
you uh pick an interconnect topology are
firstly just what are the main
operations like collectives you're going
to do on there. Um
how do you keep like interconnect
latency down? Um and then how do you
scale up really well? And so we're in
the same sort of family of what the all
of the players are doing. We don't have
like um
like totally different off-the-wall
ideas, but we uh the way we've we've
tuned it is I think pretty nice. Mhm.
He's just like so
Wow.
Okay, so like you have this chip that
doesn't exist yet, right? And you like
want to run some workload on it and the
workload also doesn't exist yet. So like
obviously modeling is is pretty
important. Um how do you think about
this, right? Like like Do you have any
takes on on how performance modeling
should look and and and what you're
doing? Yeah, yeah. I think uh I mean I
think at baseline let's just like
to set expectations like performance
modeling is so much more important in um
AI workloads than just the how people
tune and optimize AI workloads than what
we've seen before. Like if you contrast
with like the work of a someone doing
performance engineering on a CPU versus
on a GPU or like AI workload. Um
And when we're doing uh AI workloads, we
reason about percentage percentage of
peak performance. And we think we can
get like 70%, 90%, 50%, something in
that range.
Percentage of peak performance on a CPU,
what does that even mean? Like are you
ever going to be able to utilize all the
flops or like percent like can you
utilize all of the branch predictor
performance? Like how how can you even
reason about that? And so like as a
starting point, the first thing you do
when optimizing like an LLM is you sit
down and say what do I expect the
performance to be?
One of the things that uh actually I
remember like first hearing this from
Gaurav Agrawal, who was um
at Google and now at OpenAI, um is like
what is what is your goal when you're
doing performance modeling? Um like you
might think my goal is to make a
performance estimate that is as precise
as possible.
But there's no end to that, right?
Because like as precise as possible
means I start off modeling the
coarse-grained things like memory
bandwidth and compute performance. And
then I go finer grained and I look at um
uh maybe how the instructions are
scheduled against my resources. And then
maybe I even have to I could be even
more precise than that and say well,
what's the power modeling? Am I am I
going to get thermally throttled?
There's no end to it, right? Like you
just keep going. Um
So where do you stop with performance
modeling is is sort of a interesting
meta-question. And so the question is
like maybe I'm trying to get
good enough to answer a question that
I'm I'm trying to answer.
So there's a few different takes on
that, but I I think like there's this
perennial theme of how can I approximate
to answer the question faster?
Which I don't know. At least for for me
like learning this in school I hated it,
right? Like we we went to like spend a
lot of time in physics class class and
they kept saying you should approximate.
And like it's crazy. Like you're like
I've got this question, I can solve it
exactly, and they're saying you should
approximate it rather than solving it
exactly. It like
uh it defies some kind of moral
aesthetic that you have about like why
are you throwing stuff out? Um
But I I at least for me I found like
this really turned around when I'm
actually trying to answer questions
quickly and like even in my head. And
approximation is totally necessary
there. So one of the exercises that like
to go through this is like how can you
figure out which approximations to make?
How are you comfortable decide like
making these approximations but not
those approximations? And what is the
sort of principled rationale behind
that?
Um we have some like mathematicians on
our team with a very strong mathematical
background and they're like
approximations like
I want to prove something, how do I do
that when I'm approximating? Um
So one theme here is
you're not trying to prove the
performance is exactly this. That's too
hard to prove. You'll never finish. Um
and so maybe you're trying to prove
something. If you want to view it
through the lens of what am I trying to
prove, you would like to bound the
performance. So performance cannot
possibly be a bit better than this.
Roofline analysis is like the kind of
canonical example of that.
Um
uh but you can actually like do that
kind of analysis in in lots of contexts.
Um sometimes you prove the opposite,
which is like the performance will be at
least this good. That's that's a harder
thing to do, but
um or maybe you do asymptotic
performance, but that's not so like um
it throws out too much information.
Like doesn't distinguish between 30%
AMFU and 90% AMFU.
Um
But uh
a theme of can I prove an upper bound um
I think is sort of the strongest
like provable and how to go about
things. Now is that upper bound useful?
Like if I have an upper bound saying the
performance will be better than 100%,
that's not very useful. Um and then I
measure it and I find actually it's 1%,
and so well, it is within that upper
bound, but it's totally useless. Um so,
then you have to think about like what's
the tightness of my my bound. So, like
it can't be better than 50%. I've got
30% in reality. That's actually
reasonably tight. Um
what is the tightness gap? Now,
uh
and there I say there's a tightness gap
that's maybe coming because of when I
look at my profile when I'm actually
running it, um there was this what is
the single biggest effects that I didn't
model there and maybe if I include that
in my modeling now, I can say my bound
is not 50% but it's 35%. Uh and so, now
it becomes increasingly tight. That is a
sort of
like a
s- uh
a mathematical basis that I think has
sound principles to to reason about. And
I think sort of like that's in in the
back of uh my mind always when when
doing performance modeling. I would say
like we don't really always formalize it
cuz it's a bit too laborious like
proving theorems every single time, but
but that's the kind of proof you would
look for.
Um
I think
like curiously, if you think about what
theorems can I prove in other contexts,
there's kind of a branch and bound thing
going on where like I've got a search
space over chips that I want and I say,
well, I could consider chips that have
this certain characteristic. Can I
immediately bound the performance of
anything in that class and say,
no matter what I do, if I make this one
design decision, I can't possibly get
good performance. This is like the HBM
SRAM thing. Yeah, for example. Um and
so,
uh
yeah, exactly. So, like there's actually
a proof you can do that there that you
look at like the relationship between
the number of uh interconnect hops, um
the amount of capacity, you can look at
the capacity and connect it to the batch
size via Little's Law, um and you can
sort of prove bounds on the uh
utilizable flops um there.
Or um or maybe I've got a system where
I've got two two chips inter-
interacting with like completely
different resource profiles, um
can I prove a bound on like
uh any way I connect them, this chip is
going to limit the performance of that
chip or something like that. Um
And so, uh I think sort of the exercise
always when trying to prove it is like
um prove the bound and then like
actually like prove the upper bound on
performance can't be better than this
and then um actually work something out
in detail and say, well, I can achieve
this and then and then look at the
tightness there. Um so, yeah, HBM SRAM
is is one of the strongest places we've
done that um and like I I think that
from first principles that sort of just
says SRAM for these kinds of workloads
can't um
can't be attractive uh SRAM alone. And
you can then also examine your
assumptions about about model
architecture like a model has at least
100 layers or has at least a certain
amount of bytes of KB cache per per
token or something like that. Um and
sort of like just do the exercise of
exploring way we do that.
Mhm. And and just to give some clarity
to this, like what does this exercise
look like in practice, right? Like how
are you like like is is is there some
like big spreadsheet that you're like
plugging numbers into or are you like
writing out proofs here? Like what does
this look like, right? And then like how
how does this play into the process of
designing the chip, right? Like is it
like you do a couple of rounds of
iteration, you do some like simulation
here? Um what does this sort of
end-to-end process look like to
you know, kind of arrive at like what
configuration in this space you actually
want to go with? So, we we have big
spreadsheets a lot. Um and those
normally like uh
those are normally saying what we
believe is achievable or we can
demonstrate in very high fidelity, we
can at least achieve this if not better.
Um
big spreadsheets, Python modeling, um
uh like writing out instruction traces,
all of those things are ways of saying
this is achievable. Um the the upper
bounds actually we try and um minimize
the the assumptions of the proof as much
as possible. And so, those end up being
quite short actually. So, um
like it's sort of like the can you see
it at a glance? Like can I prove an
upper bound that relates only like three
variables together or five variables
together um to the point where I can do
that in my head. Um uh so, we we do that
exploration a few iterations and I mean
a lot of this is stuff that we would do
very early in a chip project um and that
tends to uncover um
like your goal is to like eliminate as
many variables from the from the bounds
as you can to like make it a stronger uh
result, especially if you can eliminate
actually hyper parameters about the
model architecture because like you
don't want to say like this chip works
for models that have like a D model
dimension of 8,000, but if it goes to
16,000, then it's not going to work
because like that's that's way too
specific. Um and so, uh
like to take tensor parallelism as an
example, um you tend to find and this is
like there's like actually the scaling
book on on performance estimation for um
tensor parallelism and and expert
parallelism talks about this. You tend
to find and this is just how it
turns out is that um
you you get results of like how big of a
matrix per chip rather than how big of a
matrix in total. Then you can read like
that's actually sort of nicer to reason
about in hardware and say, well, okay,
well, then that actually tells me how
big my SRAM should be. Mhm. So, a lot of
those calculations early on in
coarse-grained sizing of HBM SRAM
interconnect flops. Um
as it proceeds, um we do the same kind
of methodology but into the
finer-grained details like um what
should the ratio of my um
uh sorting performance versus my matrix
performance or my um like softmax
performance to matrix performance or
something like that be. And and there
again like if you're trying to minimize
it, it it's maybe connected to what is
the um minimum efficient contraction
size that I'm going to support in my
chip. Um
or uh
uh sort of what level of sparsity do I
support is connected to the amount of uh
feature these resources. Right. And and
sort of like how long is this design
process, right? Where you're sort of
like going back and forth between
um whatever your like sort of latest
state is on on on the design and then
and then sort of going back to like
modeling things out again. And also like
I don't know, like in in this whole sort
of design process, right? Like what is
the longest step, right? Like what takes
the most time? Like um is is it like the
verification? Is it just like I don't
know, like writing out the code and then
like doing this doing this like modeling
exercise and like coming back and
looking at your assumptions?
Yeah, um I mean it it depends on how you
want to run um such a project. There is
sort of the minimum viable product angle
on on a chip design and and then there's
also the um sort of
sort of uh rich design um philosophy.
And we we as a company have leaned more
in the latter style um which is I would
say somewhat against Silicon Valley um
norms which is like you you start a
startup, you ship a chip uh very quickly
and iterate. Um but like reflecting the
reality of this market, um
chip tape outs are very expensive
especially when you include all the
downstream deployment costs um and we're
also competing against like uh TPU V7
and uh like very uh mature uh GPU
products. Um we have chosen to to do
quite a like a mature design which is
sophisticated in many different axes uh
simultaneously. That has led to I mean
combination of that and like like we're
substantially innovating on the way we
um do our numerics and uh connect uh all
all of the cores of the chip together
and so on. We've spent a a reasonable
amount of time on the um
uh actually early stage architecture and
really tuning that and and mapping that
to uh what information we have about
models and what we see as that changes.
Um but then downstream of that there is
like the actual implementation of the
chip is actually quite a long process as
well. So, uh
1 to 2 years is is is common for for
many places. I I guess like on the on
the topic of modeling, right? Like I
mean part of the question here is like
what are you modeling, right? It's like
you you have some some like LLM in mind,
right? And and I I think though like the
the workloads tend to differ like differ
a lot between like prefill and decode,
right? So, like how how do you reason
about that divide? Um
I think like you know, like I think this
also sort of plays into like
fundamentally what your chip is designed
for and like what the tradeoffs you're
making here, right? Like how are you
trading off between these two things?
Yeah, so I mean I would say
uh
like
so, how are prefill and decode
different? Prefill is very demanding on
compute performance, has relatively
little demands on on memory bandwidth.
Um decode is the opposite there. Um
and yet we run them on the same chip. Uh
everyone runs it on the same chip. Maybe
there's some area for specialization of
of chips and video has done a little bit
of that, but they're basically still the
same chip with very small modifications.
So,
we're constrained that we want both of
them to run well on the same hardware
and yet the resource footprints are the
same. That can't possibly go well. Like
something's something's wrong there. And
then like even more than that, not even
considering the hardware, but um
everything about how we train a model uh
is oriented towards supporting decode.
That means I can incrementally add new
tokens. Um there's this causal mask.
Causal mask prevents things like um
uh bidirectional attention. Um there are
so many places that the constraints of
decode show up um in how I train a model
and they're just totally irrelevant for
for prefill. And so,
uh
like I would say in some sense these are
like I I I I see that and I hear like
warning sign like something's off there.
Like we're we're applying constraints
that uh are artificial because of some
coupling between the prefill and decode
model.
So, can we eliminate that coupling? I
think is it is an interesting question.
So, where did that coupling come from?
It came from well, firstly, I train a
model and I use that for both prefill
and decode. Um and then uh what that
means is that like the decode needs to
be able to attend to the pre- to the
prefill. There's a historical answer to
that which is encoder-decoder models.
We've heard about them like T5 is that,
uh BERT is an encoder-only model. Um
the early translation models are
encoder-decoder coder models. Um they
avoid this coupling and the encoder
model can can look quite different than
the decoder model.
The main difference historically being
that it has bidirectional attention.
There are various technical reasons why
you can't actually apply that in in the
uh chatbot context. Um the biggest
problem is
so, the it's it's great. You you do you
run the encoder on the user's first
response.
And then everything after that has to be
decode because uh like you
enc- encoder models are fundamentally
not incremental at all. And so,
uh like
it's kind of a waste of effort, right?
Like 1% of the conversation I'm going to
run the encoder on and then 99% I'm
going going to run the decoder on.
That's what really that's what led to
decoder-only only models uh being in the
space. But there's there's There's huge
gap between like encoder models which
get all the tokens at once and then
decoder models which get tokens one at a
time. Um is there something in between
where we can have like a model
uh
class which gets like a batch of tokens
at a time? Like instead of
all the tokens, maybe 100 tokens at a
time or 500 tokens at a time or
something like that.
This totally works, at least
conceptually. Um and so you can sort of
split your model into two halves. The
first half gets tokens a batch at a
time. The second half gets tokens one at
a time.
Um you call the first batch your prefill
model. Call the second batch your model.
Uh the decoder model can cross attend to
the prefill model um in the same way
that encoder-decoder does cross
attention.
Um this uh like you can construct the
causal masks um such that you're not
violating causality anywhere here. Uh
it's trainable. It gives you all the
advantages of decoder-only training in
that uh you can you you can actually
have a loss function on every single
token in in the sequence.
Um
So so this is something that we've
explored a little bit. Um it's this I
mean this is sort of like it's a bit of
an out there idea and and it hasn't been
our main area of research at all. Um but
the at least the idea of if you can lift
some of these constraints,
uh maybe uh
maybe it just gives you new
opportunities that you can you can try
out. So um there are so many
ideas, especially in like the vision
transformer scenario. Vision
transformers are all uh like there's no
causal masking there. They um they're
they're actually in the encoder family
rather than the decoder family. And
there's so many interesting ideas from
that literature that
do not apply to decoder-only models
because of the causal mask.
So uh
like expert choice attention doesn't
work. It breaks It breaks the causal
mask. Um soft mixture experts or smooth
mixture experts, which is like a uh
even like more extreme than than expert
choice, uh also can apply in in contexts
like this. Um things where you
downsample uh tokens over time. So like
funnel transformer uh where you say
actually I'm going to have a
representation over multiple tokens and
then combine them together. Also breaks
causal mask, but you can apply it in a
in a prefill model. So I think it's an
interesting research direction. Um it
seems like there's so many things that
like have been thrown out because of
constraints of decoder models that could
apply there. Um
uh it's just like it's a nice thing to
to explore.
Yeah, something that stood out to me
like throughout this whole conversation,
right? Is like we've talked about
everything from like model architecture
all the way down to like I don't know
like microarchitecture on the chip,
right? And like it seems like building
out this chip project requires basically
like expertise at every level of the
stack. And like I'm kind of curious like
how how do you think about like hiring
people, right? Like in building out the
team and like scaling as as sort of like
MatX grows as a company? Yeah. I mean I
I think this is actually just what is
really exciting about being in a
hardware team. Like uh I think in a
software or ML team, like your focus is
um like up and down the stack is less
than uh in a hardware company. We have
people all the way from like ML models
through uh compiler, people are writing
um like constraint solvers in the
compiler. We have uh people writing
kernels like optimizing things like
crazy. All of that stuff similar to what
you would get in a in a lab. But then as
we go down the stack, we um we're we're
doing microarchitecture. What is
actually the circuit for a floating
point adder? Um
and then even down below that, physical
design. And then even just things like
in in the rack, like what's the
insertion force of a of a of a tray into
a rack? Um what is the
uh utility power draw? How do we like
avoid big DIDT swings at at at the at
the data center level and so on. And so
it's like I think it's I mean personally
this is why I'm I'm doing hardware.
There's much more of a clean slate and
range of things you consider. It's It's
kind of a richer space to explore.
Um
And so like that means in hiring side,
we uh we hire people with all of those
different expertises. So our company is
currently about 100 people. We have um
I'd say about 2/3 of that is hardware um
covering all of the things I said like
uh logic design, physical design,
architecture, design verification, uh
rack system, um
uh signal integrity, power integrity,
all of those things. Um and then we also
have um really strong software team
doing uh kernels, um compilers, uh
simulators, and so on. Um and then and
uh and a great ML team doing all of this
kind of ML research that we're talking
about. Um
we uh
A a very successful company here needs
to grow a lot. Um I think uh like in all
of these places we we we we'd love to
have more people and and uh yeah, we
would be very happy to. What are what
are you most excited about with MatX
over the next year? Yeah, we got a lot
of work ahead of us and I think it's
going to be pretty fun. Um
uh
ramping volume on our first generation
chip is going to be um like we the kinds
of volumes we hear people talk about,
really large. Um working on future
generation chips as well I think is
really exciting. Uh there's always this
like puzzle of how how do you uh
uh leave as little on the table while
while still making the device work
really well. Uh so like I think tons of
really interesting problems to look at.
That's that's incredibly exciting.
Looking forward to seeing what happens.
That we do.
Cool. Great.
Yeah, this is fun. Yeah.